welcome to the nth episode of under the
hood so today um today we are going to
be going really under the hood and
you'll get some insights on some of the
things we don't we don't talk very often
about but are really important so we are
talking we are going to talk about our
Engineering Systems and all the things
that um some of the things that that we
are doing to support developers and uh
you know some of the Machinery behind
the scene in in our development team and
today to talk about that uh I have yonas
with us welcome yonas thank you Vincent
so yonas tell us a little bit about
yourself what's uh what are you doing uh
in the in the BC team and what's you
know what's what's your role yeah so uh
I'm the engineering manager for the
Engineering Systems teams and I I joined
Microsoft about 15 years ago and for the
past 12 years I've been running the
Engineering Systems team over here in
different names I think we recall Bill
system one point in time and
infrastructure at some point and now
it's Engineering Systems infrastructure
is still something that infrastructure
is still something that sticks yeah
sticks a little bit Yeah but it's a it's
a lot more than just infrastructure what
you yeah and so when we talk about
infrastructure people associate that
with other things like hey can you help
me with my laptop or my windows isn't
working or sorry I I don't know really
much much about those things so just to
be clear you don't do any It stuff well
I do I do at home for for family you can
actually fix printers yeah I well that's
the one thing I cannot fix that's the
one thing that that nobody can fix all
right yeah okay so um yeah so your team
is called Engineering Systems right uh
and uh so let's start with uh talking a
little bit about builds right because
that's something that uh we do quite a
bit of quite a bit of right um so how
many you know how many what do we build
what do you build and and and how often
and you know yeah so well obviously we
build the product yeah so business
Central Business Central as a product
and then we have I think we have about a
100 repositories with code bases that we
build on a regular basis okay and I
think my team owns about 70 different
build pipelines so 100 G 100 G
repositories we have that are active and
turn bills more or less daily mhm and
not all of them are owned by my team
obviously but we kind of oversee the
bill processes and a lot of them make
sure that they work that they produce
what they need to you the outputs the
official bills that those bills are set
up correctly securely by you know
following compliance rules and like like
all of these things so what are example
can you give some examples of what this
repo uh well so so so for instance
there's a repository for the uh
developer tools team the
compiler all the visual Studio code all
the visual studio code Parts there's a
specific repository for the application
developer team where we have the app
team there's this different repository
for the platform runtime pieces the
repositories for Engineering Systems
like for the bill system itself is it's
own repository and its own codebase and
there are like all of these different
repositories like the control plane is a
big part as well right we multiple
repositories for the services that it
takes to provision and run cloud
services so that's the whole the whole
machinery
to orchestrate the cloud yeah to
orchestrate whenever it yeah so when a
customer signs up for a new environment
to provision those environments to get
it deployed when a customer connects to
the environments figuring out where to
connect in the back end Etc the
repositories for all of these different
Services some of them lump together in
one repository some of them are like one
service one repository we have a kind of
a mixed
model so if you if you're familiar with
what what we ship on the DVD uh so the
these parts are not shipped on the
obviously correct so some of the some of
the pieces you mentioned before like the
NST and uh and and things like that the
application the N the install they on
the on the DVD and on the part that we
we ship openly but all the all the code
that is orchestrating the the S the SAS
service yes uh is actually not shipped
obviously but that's also a large part
of of all code base right yeah if you
look at the amount of people we have
working on the product like the things
we to customers that are being used by
customers that's a lot of people but a
lot of people's also working on the
underlying infrastructure Engineering
Systems and control plane to make it
possible for us supp to sign up to the
product and use the product and upgrade
to new versions get hot fixes and Report
issues and get help and support and
everything so there's a lot of know code
and work that goes into that part of the
system as well so do you have some stats
on on these bills um how many you know
how many different versions are we
building so we we we yeah actually you
know let's let's start somewhere else we
we we went to get we didn't use get all
um from the beginning right obviously so
we had another internal uh internal
product which has some similar
capability than git but uh I think theol
git was much more mature and became an
industry standard so we we moved to to
kid some years ago and you were part of
that effort which was not quite
significant amount of work yes yeah yeah
so can you talk a little bit about that
yeah yeah so so we came from this Source
control system called Source Depot which
is Microsoft internally only it's not
available outside of Microsoft so many
years ago Microsoft purchased source
code for a system called perforce also
known as P4 that's a centralized Source
control system which Microsoft took
productized internally added some
features scalability performance other
features missing and then more or less
entire Mark was running on Source Depot
for many many years and being a
centralized system you know that there
are some pros and cons to that it
doesn't have any good offline experience
so you went flying or working without
internet connection you could you
couldn't edit files and stuff some of
things were quite
complicated and then kind of git came
along and became an industry standard
and Microsoft started adopting open
source much more becoming much more
friendly towards open source and kind of
figured it doesn't make sense that we
continue investing in our own source
control system anymore so let's move to
something standard and Microsoft decided
to get this answer which good decision
uh a couple of years later so we had to
migrate this really old monor repo we
had with all of the Legacy code BS for
for navis at that time right into G and
if you took a single copy of just the
latest like versions of the code and
binaries and stuff in Source Depot that
would take up something like 30
gigabytes on your disc for business
Central for example just business
Central source code so we had a ton of
binaries and source code in that
repository and git doesn't really do
binaries well like it does text really
well but not binaries so we had a really
complicated process of moving binaries
out of source Depot creating Sim links
on dis to make it look like it actually
was still on the dis so then moving the
code into git we could build based on
the code based init and sings to to the
uh to the binaries and then gradually
moving these things out into packages
and redoing the code base and uh kind of
moving that way into get but a long
interesting product we had to replay
history from all sours Depot into git to
some extent so we can get history and
then we had to write Bridges so people
could go and look in and history from
git all the way back to the beginning of
source ape so we would go and open up
the Old Source ape browser to look at
history when you past the history we had
in get so yeah and you still have
requirements to be able to build older
versions for various you know compliance
but also support purposes you know like
somebody has a bug on an old version we
should be able to potentially fix it
especially if it's a security b or so
all the versions We
support uh at least officially back in
time we need to be able to at all time
be able to build them uh should some for
example a security incident occure uh
would have to provide a patch for it so
that that puts a lot of requirement on
on on your team yeah we keep on building
old versions quite a bit still to be
able to do security fixes like you
mentioned yeah if if needed if needed
yeah yeah so so with the uh you know if
you're familiar with G you know that
there is this concept of branches right
so we have uh we have quite a few
branches in our in our repo um yeah I
mean yeah definitely so it so there are
many branches which we call official
branches and official branch branches
are branches where we publish official
bills out of so those are bills we ship
to customers in one way or another
different shapes and forms right uh and
then obviously there are tons of
branches across repositories for when
people do feature development they share
work between teams or they do private
tests Etc so but not counting that there
are still a lot of branches and I
actually brought a a slide we can look
at yeah you have some uh some numbers
and statistics on yeah a little bit of
numbers on on the amount of active
branches we have
so so on the y- AIS here you can see the
different branches that we maintain and
are active where we produce builds and
there's about 30 of them so 30 different
versions where we produce builds out of
U business Central so it's more or less
is it fair to say that there's at least
at the minimum one branch per version
yes we have like even the minor version
we have a branch for that yeah exactly
and on the xax is you can see the
activity in terms of official bills on
these branches so how often do we
produce assembled entire product and
make it R for shipping MH you can see
like so in the last 60 days we did that
almost 800 times in master and in the
25x branch we did it almost 600 times so
what's master so master and Main is the
same thing that's where we develop the
next version of business okay so it's
not yet it's not shipped to customers
not shipped that's where all the that's
where the active development happens the
new stuff is happening and uh eventually
we Branch out for releases and we ship
out of release branches so we can go on
hot fix issues that customers so we have
Master which everybody all our
developers work on yes and then when we
ship say 25 then we Branch out for 25
for 25 but then everybody continues
working they continue in master and then
as they develop new features if some of
those features are also shipped in a
minor then they backport that from the
master Branch into the 25 you know one
or two br or whatever whenever they want
those things to ship all right yeah and
then and so and for each of these
branches we build the entire product we
do yeah over and over again every time
we need it like like every day or every
night or all the well I mean so if you
if you look at the the main branch for
instance we built it 800 times in the
last two months so it's a 20 times a day
or something we produce new builds new
versions so every time anybody CHS the
product if you check a new code to the
product every single change produces a
new build which we deploy to test
environments run all the tests on them
Etc to make sure that it works yeah and
and do we build what about the the
language version I mean has many
language versions yeah so with every
commit we rebuild every single language
version so everything all 30 something
languages so that's a lot of bills it we
use a lot of compute Power Engineering
system teams like we have up to 3,000
and machines running on a daily basis
doing nothing but building and testing
the product okay and it's all it's all
automated it's 100% automated the
developer checks in code gets it
reviewed and you know eventually the
bill is produced and uploaded and and
uploaded into test environments ET so so
just to be clear the the automation
basically is what your team has been you
know developing and maintening and and
you know um so you mentioned tests um
and there was there's Al some test that
gets run uh also on a regular basis also
in an automated fashion yeah so with
every I also have a slide on that so
let's take a look at this one so this
slide shows us on the xaxis it shows us
the day from January 1st to January 23rd
and on the y-axis you can see the amount
of tests we want on those every single
day so January 1st and a a lot of people
are working we just run some stability
jobs and test and we run about 20
million test cases but then like people
get back slow they get back into work
etc so if you look at January 9 for
instance we ran almost 80 million tests
wow uh on that single day on the product
so and this is a combination of running
tests on different versions
localizations and different test jobs by
build jobs PR validation official jobs
performance test all sorts of things so
we we run yeah I think on average yeah
40 million tests every day something
like that wow so what happens when one
of these tests
fails uh so it depends if they fail on
your pool request validation then we
reject your code changes then we say you
can't check it in so we're talking about
getting basically changes right so so
any change that breaks the build or uh
or even before that so so yeah if the
build if if there's build they don't get
into the build unless the test passes M
but the uh the pr validation is quite
complicated imagine like
every official build runs about half a
million test cases so with the pr
validation we do turn based test
selection so depending on what you
change in the product we run different
tests and use that to determine if you
broke something or not so you have to
some euristic to determine which test
you'll be running depending on which
part of the code yeah so we collect code
coverage for all of the test that runs
in the product and then we also know all
of the inputs and outputs so we collect
uh statistics from f system so we know
every single file that's been read by
any build task and all the outputs that
were produced by that bill task so if
you CH modify three files in part of
your pull request we can tell these
files were part of these build tasks
these build jobs so now we need to rerun
those and all the children of those and
all the tests associated with those
parts of the tasks I'm pretty impressive
so rather large system so it's fair to
say so you you you're working a lot with
Automation in general so it's fair to
say that your team is pretty good at
that yes to yeah I mean that's what we
do like a core tenant of our team is to
minimize or remove any manual processes
it wouldn't be scalable to have a team
doing any of these things manually so
it's most it's so everything when you
you know all the thing all the things
I'm talking about is is automated it's
all running automated and when any of
those processes fail we get signals and
bugs and things like that and that's
where we have sometimes have to step
into the manual things when things are
failing we need to investigate and
mitigate or fix bucks and rerun things
so then we might kick off a new
automation process again manually then
manually we started manually but then it
runs automatically it just runs
automatically I got it what about so uh
what about security you also have a
important role in ensuring we prod prod
product already secure right yeah yeah
so if you look at the last couple of
years supply chain attack is on the rise
so there are lots of examples where
companies manage to compromise
Engineering Systems Packaging Systems
npm n get and all these things and the
companies get bad code into the build
environments and then attackers manage
to move laterally from the bill systems
ET so that's yeah so that's a different
type of attack yes you know people maybe
the traditional they don't attack the
production in system they attack the
system before it heads into production
which is probably more efficient if you
succeed because well if you can sneak
bad code into a product you can do bad
things yeah imagine I don't know sales
processing if you could you know charge
the customer twice once for the actual
merchandise they're buying and one like
you know to my account or something yeah
so that would be really really bad yes
but then luckily you there to prevent
this from happening yeah well we do our
best we haven't as far as we know we
haven't had any attacks but yeah we
spend a significant amount of time on
security so can you give a few examp of
what these activities um are yeah so
there's a lot of work currently with the
safe uh future initiatives within
Microsoft which has a lot of different
work streams in how we lock down systems
so that's part of it but then we also do
other things like we Baseline all
security settings we have across all our
repositories who make sure nobody has
permissions to anything they shouldn't
have no code gets into repository
without at least one full-time employee
signs off on it and if it's release
branches at least two different persons
need to sign off on it so we manage all
of these policies and make sure that
nobody has access to things they
shouldn't have and anytime any
permissions are changed in the system we
get notified and we review these new
permission changes and we either roll
them back or we update the baselines so
I I think we review these baselines
almost every day when things are
changing to make sure that you know you
don't have permissions to something
shouldn't have we make sure nobody has
persistent access to build pipelines
release pipelines code anything like
that feeds yeah if you can inject
something into a build feed you get npm
whatever then you can sneak in code into
the build so we need to make sure that
can't happen so we run component
governance and all types of tools and
all the packages we use to make sure
they haven't been compromised and so we
know exactly which component we using
and where they come from and yes exactly
and then we generates you know s bumps
and things to indicate what's part of
the build every single version that is
an input for the build system what about
certificates um you also you know we
we're using all sorts of certificates to
uh yeah so those certificates are
generate by Microsoft through the onert
system and they're we don't we don't
have access to those they're stored in
key volts only and then we have specific
identities that the bill system runs
under for the parts that needs those
certificates that can read them from
that uh keybo and then they get Auto
rotated frequently so they change on a
regular basis they change on a regular
basis if somebody could hold of one of
the certificate yeah if somebody somehow
managed to find a gap and steal one of
those certificates we can just rotate it
immediately and it happens automatically
but if we learn that the certificate was
leaked we can rotate it as well to make
sure they can't use it for anything bad
so I know it's not the case anymore but
um at some stage you had this idea of
using uh using BC as a platform uh for
building these tools so a lot of these
tools you are talking about are
automation tools but they still require
uh maybe sometime some UI to do some of
the for you were mentioning maybe
restart an automation or restart a bill
or something so so so you had this this
idea at some stage so tell us a little
bit about that I think that's a good
story yeah so one other thing we did
many years ago was that as we Microsoft
became more and more Cloud our bill
system moved from being an in-house
hosted type of Bill system to run in the
cloud itself MH and then we had to build
we had to create our own bill system
essentially right and when you create
your own bill system we didn't really
want to spend time building a UI for
that bill system MH and we found out
that BC is really good at datadriven UI
presentation declarative data driven UI
present
so we essentially connected business
Central on top of the bill system
database and created our entities that
would represent bills and jobs and these
things in BC and then our Engineers
could use BC kind of like dog fooding BC
to look at the bill system look at the
tasks running how much was left look at
log files from bills and and all these
things so you're basically you removed
all the things in BC like there's no
there was no customer yeah remove no
sales ers
we had our own application no no no
basically no really Erp no Erp yeah so
we took that at least but you still but
but you use BC to manage or build
resources in ense right so we got the UI
for free so we didn't have to build that
UI and it would work on a phone and
different browsers and all these things
like we're not experts on building UI
and dealing with JavaScript and HTML Etc
like but BC is really good at that so
you yes so you can have good UI yes
really good UI with filtering and
sorting and like all of these things and
but we don't use this anymore no
unfortunately not no we don't okay so we
move to some yeah more yeah so one of
the things approach or well we're in
integrating more and more interal devops
for the internal stuff and then for the
external open source things we're
running on GitHub so we want to be as
close to the you know retail experience
as possible it's easier when you hire
new people it's easier for our engineers
if you're looking for documentation Etc
so we integrate into these systems asra
dubs and GitHub
instead okay it makes more sense longer
term to be as that makes sense retail as
possible building your own things
building main maintaining yes so can you
tell us uh do you have any so what's
going on right now what are you working
on do you have any projects you are
excited about you want to tell us about
yeah so we have a couple of different
ones so we do some improvements
internally one of the things I'm quite
excited about is something we call
Project test tolerance as you imagine if
you run 80 million test cases every day
if just a single of those are
unstable then you get into some issues
right so this test tolerance project
Can it can track tests across multiple
different branches and different bills
and different people it can detect
through euristic if the failure you had
on your branch is related to your
changes or if it's related to some other
instabilities like I don't know 29th is
one of those leap years is typically a
day where some tests no longer work
because they never thought about Leap
Years or or you go from September to
October you go from a on digigit month
to a two-digit month there are cases
like that where developers makes
mistakes in their test case test cases
and one thing that's really frustrating
for developers is if they try to get
their code into the build and it fails
but it doesn't fail on their code it
fails on something else MH so with this
we can kind of detect that things are
failing multiple places for different
people without changes and we no longer
have to treat that as a failure we can
instead ignore it and just warn about it
so that's one thing test tolerance super
interesting
thing then more on the like external
side of things we also work on algo for
GitHub okay which is like this kind of
simple engineering system but for
partners they can use they can bring
their own code and they can build
applications and extensions to BC and
one thing the team is working on that
Freddy is is driving now is incremental
bills so if you have a lot of projects
that you're building as part of your uh
your builds your cicd pipelines and you
only modify one of them we would only
rebuild that one and we take the outputs
from the previous build for the other
inputs so faster turn around time much
faster turnaround time and also that
means that when you deploy your changes
to your test environments or to your
sandbox you only have to redeploy one
app instead of 10 or
so the turn around time the feedback
loop becomes much quicker yeah so
talking about which one of the you know
some of the CH of your team is also to
support our developers internally like
from the BC engineering team so um so
yeah you're doing a lot of things for
keeping them happy yeah well we try yeah
yeah so what are what what are the
things you you you provide you what kind
of service you provide to our
developers give us a few examples yeah
so we listen to a lot of their feedback
and we listen to what is it that they
find um frustrating annoying with the
engineering system so like our team owns
everything from the environment where
they write their code to getting the
code actually shipped to customers
through DVDs or install as hot fixes in
SAS Etc so we get feedback around all of
these things and then you know some
sometimes we onboard some new services
for developer environments like new
Microsoft new devbox offerings then we
make sure we create images that are good
for our Engineers to to work on so so if
if I'm a developer in DC like let's say
I'm a newly hired right um why I can
just start developing you know I don't I
don't need to install anything or now so
you so you you just go to a website and
you you say Okay create Dev box you give
it a name and you give a size
essentially how big do you want it to be
do you want 8 CPUs 16 CPUs or 32 CPUs
you deploy it and the image it deploys
with has all the tools installed that
you need to build the code and then you
can start coding right yeah you you you
clone the git repository and then you
can start coding directly you don't need
to care about the dependence and stuff
so you have cql installed there's SQL
and there's compilers and
like case and do code all the things
that you require the things that you
normally would yeah yeah I just said I
can tell you an anecdote about that
because U uh one of U people in our team
was trying to set up a machine so
basically his own laptop with the own
environment then of course you can do
that yourself then you need to install
the product uh you need to install you
know all the things the tools SLE server
Visual Studio code all the sdks and all
that's doable but then you know um when
when compiling you know it was the our
app it was really really slow to deploy
right and uh so we kind of talked about
it that's weird because on my death box
that's that that's pretty fast and what
was talking a factor I don't know 10 or
something maybe not 10 but from 5
minutes to to 15 minutes right and uh
then we figure out that uh there's a
whole bunch of uh virus scanning that
happens uh on your on your laptop on
your laptop so so especially you know
things around the NST that get scanned
uh and these are pretty big uh uh files
so so uh so that we figure out that was
that was kind of the the the the problem
and uh yeah so when we set up these
boxes we add exclusions for the virus
scanner for specific folders and types
of and processes based on our
experiences of what needs to be done so
just to be clear this is still very
secure this is not we do V scanning of
everything just because this is just a
development environment the code doesn't
ship without going
through a lot of testing is and
typically you are building you know we
trust the code we write ourselves yes so
so this is the code that not does not
get scan because this is what get ex
change typically when you when it gets
reviewed by at least mult yeah multiple
people will review your code before it
gets to production yeah yeah so that's
pretty cool um I just saw recently also
your team just made a new uh Improvement
to our deployment system so we would
have uh so all developers now have a a
fully deployed a share test tenant yeah
share test tenant they can access
practically wide away with the latest
bits from from Master yeah so that's
another example of such an improvement
we do when we hear about the frustration
around getting easy access to test
deployments so all of the all of the
developers can access all of the
official builds get deployed and they
can just go to the browsering they go to
a URL and then they can pick between
which bills they want to test and get
signed into BC for that one
automatically as opposed to before they
had they would have to go through the
signup flow sign up flow and it will
take some time and you know before you
actually had a a full environment now
it's just really
that's pretty cool so they can test and
yeah and the same thing for private
branches so if you're working on a
feature in your team or yourself you can
submit a test job that does this
deployment for you and when that's done
it shows up in this environment as well
so you don't have to sign up to that as
well you just go into the browser you
can test your latest code I haven't
tried yet but sure yeah will it was a
great
Improvement so um um I think quite a few
of our partners out there have uh have
different um you know um systems similar
to to ours at different levels some of
them are you know simpler some of them
are quite complex yes so do you have a
do you have any advice for partners in
building you know Engineering Systems
and you know how should they go about it
is that something they should uh invest
a lot I would say stay away from it if
you
can no I I would piggy back on one that
is already out there and something like
aure devops yeah so aure devops and if
they're work on Al code I would probably
go for something like Al go for GitHub
alpaka Al you know Al devops and like
there are solutions out there I would
recommend building on those instead of
creating your own from scratch it's
become very complicated to keep these
things secure and and staying up to date
with all the things happening in the
industry these days so unless you have
very special needs and even with that I
mean this this I would rather customize
already available system than create my
own these but when you say it's when you
say it's it's a good thing to have at a
minimum some automated build so you can
build on a regular basis yeah I I don't
understand how you would how you would
be able to work in today's landscape
without having automated bills tests
deployments that
happens Version Control you need you
need builds uh you need you know a pull
request or yeah a review process for
looking at the code getting it reviewed
you need a way to test your code and
deploy it and these things with some of
these systems like Al go for GitHub
these things are they come out of the
box even the test execution and
deployment to sandboxes and these things
you get that for free versus spending
then you can spend your time on what is
you want like business logic business
value that is better off yeah we'll put
some links in the comments on the
documentation of Elo for get yeah yes
which is by the way where we're trying
to move our own application team
development so we're gradually moving
them out of our internal asro devop
solution slowly it takes time we have a
large Legacy system but eventually the
goal is to have our app team dog fooding
that actually yeah dog using Al go gith
up dog food and U doing all of their
development in the public in the open
source space so contributing with
partners and sharing some of the work
taking contributions from them
Etc all right all right you thank you
for sharing all these insights on maybe
another of of BC that's less known yes
definely um I hope you enjoy this
episode and thank you for watching